Drawn by a landscape as white as snow,
真っ白な景色にいま誘われて
Masshiro na keshiki ni ima sasowarete
I'm headed toward an unseen world.
僕は行くよ　まだ見ぬ世界へ
Boku wa yuku yo mada minu sekai e
I've been traveling while lost
迷子のまま旅していた
Maigo no mama tabi shiteita
Under this gray sky.
鼠色の空の下
Nezumiiro no sora no shita
Every day with new maps, stained with my many dreams.
日替わりの地図 いくつもの夢が滲んでいた
Higawari no chizu ikutsumo no yume ga nijindeita
I wonder if someday,
いつかはさ
Itsuka wa sa
Even with these tiny steps of mine,
ちっぽけな僕のこの歩幅でも
Chippoke na boku no kono hohaba demo
I'll be able to travel beyond those clouds.
あの雲の向こうまで行けるかな
Ano kumo no mukou made yukeru kana
I put on a bold front.
強がって
Tsuyogatte
End up hurting myself.
キズついた
Kizutsuita
I feel empty inside.
心透かしたように
Kokoro sukashita youni
It's started to rain,
降り出した
Furidashita
And the raindrops
雨粒たちが
Amatsubu tachi ga
Began to repeat their scattered reflections.
乱反射繰り返す
Ranhansha kurikaesu
These straight rays of light
真っ直ぐな光が
Massugu na hikari ga
Start to cross one another.
交差して
Kousa shite
And without telling anyone where they're headed,
行き先も告げぬまま
Yakusaki mo tsugenumama
Across the endless distances,
どこまでも
Doko made mo
They pass through all matter.
突き抜ける
Tsukinukeru
I burn these faint afterimages onto my eyes.
淡い残像　両目に焼きつけて
Awai zanzou ryoume ni yakitsukete
Under this sky,
この空の下
Kono sora no shita
Wherever I am,
どんなとこにいても
Donna toko ni itemo
I should be able to reach
届くはずなんだ
Todoku hazu nanda
The unseen world.
まだ見ぬ世界へ
Mada minu sekai e
Edward, huh?
エドワードか
You've grown.
大きくなったな
I heard from Pinako...
ピナコに聞いたぞ
...that you attempted human transmutation.
人体錬成したって
今ごろ何しに戻ってきた
After all this time, why did you come back now?!
There's no place for you here anymore!
もうてめぇの居場所はねぇんだよ
Oh, right.
そうだ
Why did you burn down my house?
オレの家
なんで焼いてしまったんだ
We decided we wouldn't turn back anymore.
もう後戻りはしないって決めたんだ
We did it to show our determination-
オレたちの覚悟を示すために
That's not it.
違うな
You just didn't want to see it again.
見たくなかった
You wanted to escape your horrifying memories.
嫌な思い出から逃れたかった
しでかしたことの痕跡を隠したかった
You wanted to conceal all traces of the sin you committed.
違う
That's not true!
寝小便した子供がシーツを隠すのと一緒だ
You're no different from a child who hides
his sheets after wetting himself in his sleep.
逃げたな　エドワード
You ran, didn't you, Edward?
て　てめぇに何が分かる
What do you know?!
Damn it! You're sickening!
くそっ　胸くそ悪ぃ
He's so similar to the way I was when I was young.
オレの若いころにそっくりだな
You haven't changed at all.
変わらないねぇ
あんたは　昔のままだ
Not even a bit from the old days.
Why didn't you come back sooner?
なぜもっと早く帰って来なかったんだい
Trisha was always waiting for you.
トリシャはずっと待ってたんだよ
Pinako.
ピナコ
Hm?
The thing my sons transmuted...
息子たちが錬成したもの
Was it really Trisha?
本当にトリシャだったのか
What?
言っただろ
I told you. It didn't even look remotely human.
人の形をしてなかったって
I can't even call that thing Trisha-
あれをトリシャとは
いや　そうじゃなくて
No, that's not what I mean.
例えば瞳の色　髪の色
For example, the color of her eyes and hair.
What do you mean?
どういうことだい
You're telling me that wasn't her?
あれはトリシャじゃなかったとでも
You're telling me those boys lost their bodies by creating something that wasn't even their mother?
まったく関係ないものをつくって
あの子らは体を持ってかれたっていうのかい
ええっ　飯も睡眠もなしでずっと動ける
What?! You can continue to function without food or sleep?!
Yup, as long as this seal remains unscathed.
うん　この印さえ傷つけなければ
That's amazing! You're literally immortal!
すごい　まさに不老不死じゃないか
違うよ
That's not true.
My body is almost like a bomb.
爆弾付きなんだ　この体
I heard it from Barry.
バリーが言ってた
本来他人の魂と肉体は相いれないもの
It's impossible to place a soul that doesn't belong on a body.
無理に入れれば　拒絶反応が起きる
If you force a soul on to one, it will eventually be rejected.
それが明日なのか　１０年後なのか
Whether that will be tomorrow or ten years later...
...even I don't know.
僕にも分からないけど
そんな　じゃあすぐにでも元に戻らないと
No way... then you have to find a way to get your body back as soon as possible!
いや　でも
Wait, if your body starts to deteriorate, can't you transfer your soul on to something else and continue to live?
体がヤバくなったら
ほかのものに魂をのせ替えて　生き続けられないか
If you do that, you can stay the way you are.
もしそうなら　今のままでも
痛みを感じない　食い物もいらないんだ
Without feeling pain or needing to eat!
What a convenient body!
便利でいいじゃないかその体
Of course it's not convenient!
いいわけないでしょ
何も知らないくせに
You don't even know anything!
Sorry.
ごめん
Winry!
ウィンリィ
Winry?
ウィンリィ　入るよ
I'm coming in.
もう　いつも兄さんやウィンリィが先に怒るから
Geez... You and Brother always get mad before I ever can, so I never get to.
僕は怒るタイミングを逃しっぱなしだよ
It's because....
だって
It seems this body can't sleep...
どうやらこの体は　眠ることができないみたいだ
Al...
アル
You'll be able to return to your old body, right?
元の体に戻れるよね　ねえ
Right?
返せよ
Give me back my brother's body!
弟の体
He's... He's the only family I've got!!!
たった　たった一人の家族なんだよ
Give it back?
返せ
何を言ってるんだ
What are you talking about?
You're the one who put your brother in that state.
弟をあんな体にしたのはお前だろ
Alchemist.
錬金術師
That's right.
そう　君も私と同じだ
You and I are the same.
Edward Elric!
エドワード·エルリック
And...
それに
Edward... don't leave me like this...
エドワード　こんな姿のままじゃ嫌だわ
Ed! You still asleep?
エド　まだ寝てんのかい
Your dad's about to leave.
おやじさんが出てっちまうよ
これ　もらっていいか
Can I take this?
It's the only one that has all four of us.
四人で撮ったの　これしかないんだ
Help yourself.
別にかまわんよ
Thanks.
すまんな
As a token of my gratitude, I'll tell you something.
お礼にいいことを教えてやるよ
じきひどいことがこの国で起こる
Something terrible will happen in this country soon.
よその国へ逃げとけ
Flee to another country.
ひどいことなんて珍しくもない
That's not uncommon here.
And besides, there are kids who call this place home.
第一
ここを帰って来る場所にしてるヤツらがいるんでねぇ
忠告はしたぞ
Don't say I didn't warn you.
Hohenheim.
ホーエンハイム
Come back every now and then for a meal, won't you?
たまにはご飯食べに帰っておいでよ
It's a shame, Pinako,
残念だよピナコ
that I won't be able to eat your cooking anymore.
もうお前の飯が食えなくなるなんて
Are you really going to dig that thing up?
ほんとに掘り起こすのかい　あれを
Want to call it off?
やめるかい
No, it's just that my joints are starting to hurt.
いや
手足の付け根が痛む
雨だ
Probably because it's about to rain. Let's get this over with.
早く済まそう
Ed!
エド
I told you so!
言わんこっちゃない
Let's stop this.
もうやめよう
いや
No...
If I don't confirm it, I'll never be able to move forward.
確認しないと前へ進めないだろ
Also...
それに
You ran, didn't you?
逃げたな
No way in hell am I going to run!
逃げてたまるか
Granny.
ばっちゃん　母さんの髪は栗色だった
Mom had auburn hair.
黒だ
This is black.
The femur is way too long.
大腿骨　長すぎる
The pelvis... This is a man.
骨盤　こりゃ男のだ
Granny.
ばっちゃん
Ed.
エド
This is not your mother.
これはお前の母親ではない
That's right. You cannot revive the dead.
そうだ　死んだ人間は元に戻らない
That's a truth.
それが真理だ
It was impossible from the very beginning.
不可能なことだったんだ
Ed, pull yourself together!
エド　しっかりおし
Snap out of it!
気を確かに持つんだ
I'm fine, Granny...
大丈夫だよ　ばっちゃん
あの日からこれは絶望の象徴だった
Since that day, this has been the symbol of despair.
だが今は　希望につながる
But now, it will lead me to a path with hope.
アルは元に戻れる
Al can get his body back.
Hello, you've reached the Curtis'.
はい　カーティス
Oh, it's you, Ed.
なんだエドか　どうした
What is it?
あの　師匠に聞きたいことがあって
Umm... There was something I wanted to ask you...
ただ
Well...
なんだ　はっきり言いなさい
What's wrong?
Speak clearly.
It's about the time you tried to revive your baby...
お子さんを人体錬成したときのことなんですが
それがどうした
What about it?
Master, the person Al and I transmuted was not our mother.
師匠　オレとアルが錬成したのは
母さんではなかったんです
なんのことだ　何が言いたい
What do you mean? What are you trying to say?!
師匠が錬成してでき上がったお子さん
The child that was created by your transmutation...
本当に　師匠の子供でしたか
Are you sure it was your child?
I see...
そうかい
息子たちは戦地でよくやっとったんだね
So my son and his wife helped a lot on the battlefield, eh?
Good to know...
そうかい
He...
あいつ　ホーエンハイムはどこへ行くって
Where did Hohenheim say he was headed?
Who knows? He didn't mention a word about it.
さあね　何も
Oh, I completely forgot!
ああ　忘れとった
I had an important message for him.
ヤツに大事な伝言があったんだ
Message?
伝言
Yeah.
ああ　遺言だよ　トリシャの
Trisha's will.
あの人が帰って来たら　伝えてもらえますか
Could you pass this on to him when he comes back?
Please tell him I couldn't keep my promise.
約束　守れなかったって
先に逝きます　ごめんなさいって
That I have to leave him first, and that I'm sorry.
A promise? What promise?
約束　なんの
さあ
No idea.
Sorry to make you do this, but could you tell him for me if you see him?
すまないがあいつに会ったら伝えといてくれ
Why do I have to do it?!
なんでオレが
He may not look it, but he's actually quite worried about you two.
あれでもお前たちのこと　結構心配してるんだよ
I'll deliver the message after I give him a good punch in the face.
１発殴った後で伝えといてやるよ
Are you going back to Central?
セントラルに戻るのかい
Yeah, just to get yelled at by Al,
ああ　アルに怒られにな
since I went and did a bunch of stuff without telling him.
勝手にいろいろしちゃったからな
なんじゃこりゃ
What the hell is this?!
I'm sorry.
ごめんなさい
Y-You...
お前　こんなにぶっ壊れて
You're in ruins!
And...
それに
What the hell are you guys doing?!
お前らも何やってんだ
飯食ってます
Eating.
ったく　何があったんだよ
Geez, just what happened to you?!
Homunculi and Barry the Chopper?
人造人間にバリー·ザ·チョッパー
And on top of it all, a rejection reaction due to different souls and bodies, huh...
おまけに相いれない体と魂との拒絶反応か
Stretching the armor that's left...
残った鎧を引き伸ばしてっと
Al will be able to return to his old body, right?
アル　元の姿に戻れるよね
Of course.
当ったりめぇだ
If I say I'll get his body back, I will.
オレが戻すっつったら戻す
Al...
アル
I dug up the thing we transmuted back in Resembool.
リゼンブールで
あのとき錬成したものを掘り起こしてきた
W-Why did you do something like that?!
なっ　なんでそんなことを
As a result, I discovered that what we transmuted wasn't Mom.
結果として
あれは母さんではないということが判明した
What? What does this mean?
えっ　どういうこと　だって
But we...
We transmuted something completely different.
オレたちは　まったく違うものを錬成したんだ
No way! Then I...
そんな　それじゃあ僕は
And now, I'm also confident we can get your body back.
そして　お前が元に戻れるという確信を得た
Really?!
本当に
Yeah.
ああ　で　その話をする前に
But before I get into that...
Y-You remember the time we fought over who'd be m-marrying W-Winry... right?
ウィ　ウィンリィを　その
嫁にすんのどっちだって兄弟ゲンカしたこと
覚えてるか
The thing we talked about up on the roof?
この前屋上で話したやつ
Yeah. So you turned Al down?
ああ　アルを振ったんだって
Yeah. I did.
うん　振った振った
で　二人に質問なんだけど
And so, I have a question for you two.
Why did you turn him down?
その理由は
"I don't want to marry a guy who's shorter than me."
「私より背の低い男は嫌」
Don't decide a man's worth by his height!!!
身長で男の価値決めんなよ
Huh?
ってか　それがアルの体と何か関係あるの
Does this have anything to do with getting Al's body back?
To sum it up, if Al knows something I don't, and Winry remembers the same thing, too...
つまり　オレの知らないことをアルが知っていて
同じことをウィンリィも覚えているってことは
...it really happened.
それは本当にあった出来事だ
Since he remembers something that really happened,
it means the soul affixed to that armor is the real Al's.
本当にあったことを覚えてるんだから
鎧に定着させたのは　本物のアルだってことだよ
Even though I could only get your soul,
I was able to pull you back from that gate.
あの扉から　魂のみだが
ちゃんとお前を引っ張り出すことができた
魂が引っ張り出せたんなら
If I could pull your soul from the gate, then I should be able to get your body back the same way.
肉体も　扉の向こうから取り戻せるはずだ
Separated from each other, the body and soul still exist....
魂と離れて　なお肉体が存在
あっ　バリー·ザ·チョッパー
Barry the Chopper!
アル　思い出してみろ
Al, try to remember.
The time you were dragged into the truth.
あのとき　真理の中へ連れ込まれたときのことを
That time...
あのとき
僕だ　あそこには僕がいた
That was me! I was there!
That's right. So all I have to do...
そうだ　だから魂のときと同様
...is pull your body out like I did with your soul!
肉体も引っ張り出せばいいんだ
Brother!
兄さん
僕はあのとき
I was watching you from that thing's point of view!
母さんだと思っていたものの中から　兄さんを見ていた
あれに入っていたのは　お前だったのか
So it was you inside that thing?
The soul probably didn't affix due to the rejection reaction.
たぶん　拒絶反応のせいで　魂が定着しなかったんだ
So we didn't damage anyone's soul...
僕たち　誰の魂も傷つけてはいなかったんだ
Sir Elric.
エルリック様
Miss Izumi Curtis is on the line.
イズミ·カーティス様からお電話です
I looked into the family lineages of both my husband and me.
私の家系と　だんなの家系を調べてみた
結果　錬成されたあの子の肌の　色髪の色
As a result, the skin and hair color of that child...
共に私たち夫婦から生まれるはずのないものだった
...cannot possibly have come from the two of us.
You were able to find something out, weren't you?
何か突き止めたんだな
Yes.
はい　アルの体を取り戻せる確信と
Confidence that I'll be able to get Al's body back...
It's impossible to revive the dead.
死んだ人間をよみがえらせることは不可能
I see...
そうか
何かが足りなかったのではなく
It wasn't that I was missing something...
そもそもできないことか
...but rather it was impossible from the very beginning.
Ed.
エド
Yes, ma'am!
はい
Thank you.
ありがとう
What did the master say?
師匠　なんて
よく分かんねぇけど
I don't really get it, but she thanked me.
ありがとうって言われた
アル
Al?
To be honest, I've been blaming myself nonstop since that day.
僕ね　あの日からずっと自分を責めてきた
That it was me...
母さんを　あんな姿にして殺したのは僕だと
...who put Mom in that state and killed her.
Same goes for me, Al.
オレもだよ　アル
Thank you, Brother...
ありがとう　兄さん
I didn't kill Mom!
僕は母さんを殺してはいなかった
Izumi.
イズミ
救われた気がするんだ
I feel saved.
私はあの子を二度殺してはいなかった
I didn't kill our child twice...
But it's true that I put you in that state.
だが　オレがお前の体をそんなふうにしたのは事実だ
I'm going to get your body back, no matter what-
なんとしてもオレは　お前の体を元に
兄さん
Brother!
We carry the same sin, since I approved of the plan.
あれは賛同した僕も同罪なんだから
一人で背負ってるようなこと言わないでよ
Please don't talk as though it's all your fault.
なんでも一人で抱え込んで
Trying to do everything by yourself...
I'm tired of other people having to suffer because of me!
僕はもう　自分のことで
ほかの人が犠牲になるのは嫌なんだよ
Same with Mr. Hughes, too!
ヒューズさんのときだって
死んだって知ったとき
When I heard about his death...
I felt from the bottom of my heart I didn't want to return to my body if other people would have to suffer.
ほかの人が犠牲になるくらいなら
元に戻らなくてもって正直思ったしね
Brother...
兄さん
人ならざる体を持っていても
...even if they don't have the body of humans...
...I've been watching people who live according to the way they are.
自分らしく生きる人たちを見てきた
こんな体でも　周りの人は
Even if I'm in this state, people around me interact with me as though I'm human.
人間として接してくれる
I know my body's like a bomb, but even a body made of flesh could die from accident or disease at any time.
爆弾付きっていったって
生身の体でも　いつ事故や病気で死ぬか分からないんだ
So in order to live a normal life,
this body isn't all that inconvenient either.
だから普通に生きる分には　この体でも不自由はない
I've truly started to feel that way.
そう思うようになってきた
But...
でも
...I can't stand it any longer.
やっぱりダメだ
もう　もう
I'm... I'm...
一人の夜は嫌なんだ
...tired of spending nights by myself!
That's my reason for wanting to return to my old body.
それが　元に戻りたい理由だ
Yeah, I'll make it happen.
ああ　やってやるさ
真理の野郎をぶっ飛ばして
After I beat the shit out of that "truth" guy, I'm going to drag your body out of there!
あそこからお前の体を引っ張り出してやる
Yeah!
うん
Huh?
あいつ
Has he always had such a large back?
あんなに背中大きかったっけ
Let it all out, Let it all out
I don't have to act tough, right?
強がらなくていいんだね
Tsuyogaranakute iindane
The scribbling someone made...
誰かが描いてった
Dareka ga kaitetta
On the wall, of a flower is swaying.
壁の落書きの花が　揺れる
Kabe no rakugaki no hana ga yureru
No one knows their true selves.
自分らしさなんて, 誰もわからないよ
Jibunrashisa nante dermo wakaranaiyo
Even though we both lose and gain
長い長い道の途中で
Nagai nagai michi no tochuu de
By embarking on this long, long path,
失くしたり, 拾ったり,
Nakushitari hirottari
And though there may be days loneliness strikes and makes us weep...
急に寂しくなって, 泣いちゃう日もあるけど
Kyuu ni samishikunatte naichau hi mo arukedo
Let's transform our tears and pains to stars.
涙も　痛みも　星に変えよう
Namida mo itami mo hoshi ni kaeyou
Let's light a candle to illuminate our tomorrow.
明日を照らす　灯りをともそう
Ashita wo terasu akari wo tomosou
And we'll hold our small hands over the fire to create stardust,
小さな手かざして　ふたりで作ろう
Chiisana te kazashite futari de tsukurou
And an eternity that shines so brilliantly.
星屑を　強く光る永遠を探そう
Hoshikuzu wo tsuyoku hikaru eien wo
Farewells may be unavoidable,
さよなら　いつかは来るかもしれない
Sayonara itsuka wa kurukamoshirenai
Yet the seasons continue to change obliviously.
季節はそれでも巡り巡ってく
Kisetsu wa soredemo meguri megutteku
Even if I lose myself, I'll continue to walk...
小さく迷っても　歩いてく
Chiisaku mayottemo aruiteku
Walk by your side.
君と歩いてく
Kimi to aruiteku
That's the only thing I'd like to never change.
それだけは変わらないでいようね
Sore dake wa kawaranaideiyoune
日本語字幕仕上げ：FAYFAY
傷ついた仲間の姿は
The figure of a wounded comrade hurries the man's steps,
男の歩みを加速させ
漫遊字幕組
http://popgo.net/bbs
少年は袋小路を脱するために
and the boy risks everything he has to escape a dead end.
乾坤一擲の勝負に出る
次回　鋼の錬金術師
Next time, Fullmetal Alchemist:
FULLMETAL ALCHEMIST
第二十一話　愚者の前進
Episode 21, Advance of the Fool.
戦いの火ぶたは　自ら切って落とせ
You shall be the one to open fire.